{"tossups": [{"question": "A poet from this country lamented \"don't die Dad / but they die\" in a poem that concludes \"fuck the\u0301m; I wish you God\" and is titled \"The Last Hellos\"; that poet from this country, who wrote \"axe fall, echo and silence\" in his poem \"Noonday Axeman,\" penned the collection Subhuman Redneck Poems and is named Les Murray. A literary journal in this country called Angry Penguins published work by James McAuley and Harold Stewart that was attributed to the \u28b8ctional poet \"Ern Malley.\" The line \"down came the Policemen: one, two, three\" appears in a poem from this country about a man who \"waited till his billy boiled\" before singing beneath a \"coolibah tree.\" For 10 points, name this home country of Banjo Paterson, whose \"bush ballads\" include \"Waltzing Matilda.\"", "answer": "Australia [or Commonwealth of Australia]", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This poem describes an entity that \"makes the willow shiver in the sun\" for maidens who \"taste / and stray impassioned in the littering leaves.\" This poem asks whether \"boughs / hang always heavy in that perfect sky\" at a place where there might be \"no change of death.\" The first section of this poem concludes with a comparison of the day to \"wide water\" that is \"stilled\" so that \"dreaming feet\" might pass \"over the seas, to silent Palestine.\" The \"coffee and oranges in a sunny chair\" lead a woman to question the divine promise of paradise in this poem, which repeats that \"death is the mother of beauty\" and opens by describing the \"complacencies of the peignoir\" (pay-NWAHR). For 10 points, name this poem by Wallace Stevens that is set in the early hours of the Lord's day.", "answer": "\"Sunday Morning\"", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A philosopher in this novel decides that the \"li0man in the Tube is an eternal necessity\" but that the \"arts are merely a decoration imposed on the top of human life.\" During a walk on the beach in this novel, four characters sing \"damn your eyes, damn your eyes\" before Minta learns she has lost her grandmother's brooch. In this novel, a boy who likes to cut pictures out of an Army and Navy Stores catalogue is crushed when his father predicts that the weather will be poor the next day. Parentheticals note that Prue died in childbirth and Andrew was killed at war in its middle section, \"Time Passes.\" Lily Briscoe \u28b8nishes a painting and James and his father take a boat out to the title structure in the Hebrides at the end of, for 10 points, what Virginia Woolf novel about the Ramsay family?", "answer": "To the Lighthouse", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "The infinitesimal generators of this operation in 3D are elements in the algebra defined by the Lie (LEE) bracket of L-sub-k and L-sub-l equals the totally antisymmetric 3-dimensional tensor times L-sub-m. The Lie group corresponding to this operation in 2D has a two-by-two infinitesimal generator in the form of the matrix zero, minus one (pause) one, zero. The special orthogonal group is the group of this isometry's \"proper\" type. In quantum mechanics, its operator interconverts spin-up and spin-down particles and is generated by the angular momentum operator. Symmetry under this operation equates to conservation of angular momentum by Noether's (NOY-turr's) theorem. For 10 points, for what type of motion does the cross product of lever arm and force cause acceleration, also known as torque?", "answer": "rotational motion [or circular motion; or angular motion]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "The North American Review commissioned a \u28b8nancier and businessman from this industry to write essays on foreign policy, including \"Americanism versus Imperialism\" and \"Distant Possessions.\" A 1919 strike in this industry targeted a company whose owners included Elbert Gary and future bank namesake Charles Schwab. A country club frequented by this industry's magnates built a reservoir that broke in 1889, causing the Johnstown &amp;ood. Frederick Taylor re\u28b8ned his management theories while working for a company in this industry based in the town of Bethlehem. Henry Clay Frick helped put down a strike of workers in this industry in Homestead, Pennsylvania. For 10 points, name this manufacturing industry in which Andrew Carnegie made his fortune.", "answer": "steel industry", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This thinker developed the notion of \"intuitive cognition,\" which he distinguished from \"abstractive cognition.\" This thinker used the example of the sentence \"Socrates is similar to Plato\" to show that seven out of ten of Aristotle's categories were unnecessary. This thinker, whose idealization of poverty fueled his dispute with Pope John XXII, transitioned from a \"\u28b8ctum-theory\" to an \"intellectio-theory\" to critique the idea of universal concepts in metaphysics. This thinker's textbook Summa Logicae outlines his nominalist position, which has been boiled down to the statement \"entities should not be multiplied without necessity.\" For 10 points, what Franciscan friar names a statement holding that the simplest idea is usually the correct one, which is o0en referred to as his \"razor\"?", "answer": "William of Ockham [or William of Occam; or Gulielmus Occamus; accept Ockham's razor]", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "Angela Hewitt's \"world tour\" in 2007 and 2008 was primarily devoted to complete performances of this work. This work was \u28b8rst recorded in its entirety by Edwin Fischer. Gottlieb Schwenke (SHVEN-kuh) added an extra measure to this work's opening, a 35-bar passage consisting primarily of broken chords that ends on a C-major chord. By age ten, Nadia Boulanger (boo-\"lawn\"-ZHAY) supposedly memorized the entirety of this work, whose form inspired Dmitri Shostakovich's Opus 87. Charles Gounod (goo-NOHD) composed his Ave Maria by superimposing a melody over the Prelude in C Major that opens this work, whose title refers to a method of tuning that allows one to play most keys. For 10 points, what keyboard collection by J. S. Bach contains two books of preludes and fugues that span all 24 major and minor keys?", "answer": "The Well-Tempered Clavier [or Das Wohltemperierte Klavier; or Das Wohltemperirte Clavier]", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The departure function for this quantity always includes a \"Z minus 1\" term but not a \"log Z\" term. Refrigeration cycles are trapezoidal on phase diagrams plotting this quantity against pressure. The Maxwell relation derived from this quantity sets \"partial V partial S\" equal to \"partial T partial P.\" It is the Legendre (leh-ZHAHN-druh) transform of internal energy with respect to volume. In chemical engineering, open-system energy balances are done over this quantity, which, for a monatomic ideal gas, equals \"five-halves times RT.\" Its partial derivative with temperature is defined as the constant-pressure heat capacity, and it equals the Gibbs free energy plus temperature times entropy, or \"U plus PV.\" For 10 points, what thermodynamic potential\u2014a state function according to Hess's Law\u2014is symbolized H?", "answer": "enthalpy [accept H before \"H\"; prompt on \"energy\"; do not accept or prompt on \"internal energy\"]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In this text, a child is hanged from a tree but survives and is found carving pictures of heroes into the wood. Because a stone baked into a loaf of bread causes a knife to break, a man in this text disguises bears and wolves as a herd of cattle to kill the wife of a smith. A grief-stricken mother in this text sends a bee to retrieve drops of magic honey to revive her son, who was shot and killed with an arrow while trying to retrieve a black swan from the underworld. In this text, the witch-queen of Pohjola (poh-YOH-lah) offers her daughter in marriage in exchange for a magical mill called the Sampo (SAHM-po), which is forged by Ilmarinen (\"ILL\"-mah-rin-en). Elias Lo\u0308nnrot (EL-ee-as LOON-rot) compiled, for 10 points, what poem about the heroes Va\u0308ina\u0308mo\u0308inen and Lemminka\u0308inen (\"VIE\"-nah-moy-nen and LEM-in-kye-nen) that serves as the national epic of Finland?", "answer": "Kalevala [or Kalewala]", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "This country's uni\u28b8cation into a nation-state was solidi\u28b8ed by a victory at the Battle of Slivnitsa (slihv-NEET-sah) and by the Tophane (toh-FAH-nay) Agreement. Paisius (\"PIE\"-see-us) of Hilendar was an early advocate of this country's national revival. Rebels from this nation built cannons made of cherrywood during an uprising whose brutal suppression was reported on by Eugene Schuyler (SKY-ler). As a principality and vassal state, this country was ruled by Alexander of Battenberg, who added Eastern Rumelia (ROO-mee-lee-ah) to its control. During this nation's April Uprising, bashi-bazouk (bah-shee-bah-ZOOK) troops massacred citizens, leading William Gladstone to criticize Benjamin Disraeli for failing to address this country's \"horrors.\" In 1878, the Treaty of San Stefano granted autonomy from the Ottoman Empire to, for 10 points, what Balkan country whose capital is So\u28b8a?", "answer": "Bulgaria [accept Principality of Bulgaria or Kingdom of Bulgaria or Tsardom of Bulgaria or Third Bulgarian Tsardom or Republic of Bulgaria; do not accept or prompt on \"Ottoman Empire\"]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Yoko Ono's Film no. 5 shows John Lennon facing the camera for 52 minutes and sporadically doing this action. In another \u28b8lm, a mummi\u28b8ed skull is brie&amp;y superimposed over the transition to a shot of a car being pulled out of a swamp from a shot of a man doing this action, which he begins doing after a &amp;y crawls on his hand. The cow-carrying man called Moschophoros (moh-skoh-foh-rohs) and the standing nude male called Kroisos Kouros (kroh-EE-sohs KOO-rohs) exemplify a trend in the Greek Archaic period of depicting life by having sculptural subjects do this action. Norman Bates does this action while staring into the camera at the end of Psycho. Despite its title, Frans Hals's The Laughing Cavalier shows its subject doing this action. For 10 points, what facial expression is enigmatically on display in the Mona Lisa?", "answer": "smiling [accept word forms such as smile; accept synonyms such as grinning; accept laughing or synonyms or word forms before \"laughing\"]", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "An unpopular advisor to this king was going into exile when he was intercepted by the warship Nicholas of the Tower and executed with a rusty sword. Nobles who opposed this king were subjected to bills of attainder by the Parliament of Devils. A0er a mysterious \"sudden fright,\" this king entered a months-long trance that may have been a form of schizophrenia. He disinherited his son in the Act of Accord and was brie&amp;y restored to power in the Readeption (ree-ah-DEP-shun). This king was found singing beneath a tree when his wife, Margaret of Anjou, rescued him at the Second Battle of St. Albans. His second reign ended when Yorkist forces took London after the Battle of Tewkesbury. For 10 points, what king from the House of Lancaster lost his throne to Edward IV during the Wars of the Roses?", "answer": "Henry VI of England [prompt on \"Henry\"]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A year after moving to the U.S., this man, under the umbrella of the organization ICF, founded a series of international scienti\u28b8c conferences, one of which was chaired by Nobel laureate John Eccles. This man promoted the idea that humans are restored to God's ideal by doing good things via the process of \"indemnity.\" This man, who wrote a 1966 religious text called Divine Principle, called his family the \"True Family\" and was known to followers as the \"True Father.\" The prologue to Don DeLillo's novel Mao II describes a \"blessing ceremony\" presided over by this man at Yankee Stadium. Adherents of this man's movement sold &amp;owers in airports and engaged in mass wedding ceremonies. For 10 points, name this founder of the Uni\u28b8cation Church who was a South Korean religious leader.", "answer": "Sun Myung Moon [or Mun Seon-myeong; or Mun Yong-myeong]", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "The \u28b8rst approved U.S. clinical trials using CRISPR (\"crisper\"), due to start in 2017, will edit this structure. This structure is abnormally small in Plasmodium, and in trypanosomes (trih-PAN-oh-sohmz), it is organized into several maxicircles interlocking thousands of minicircles. Petite yeast mutants are caused by defects in this structure. Haplogroups are distinguished by genes on the Y chromosome or on this structure. In humans, cytochrome c oxidase and only 36 other genes are encoded by this structure, which is circular and encodes the gene responsible for Leber's optic neuropathy. The hypothetical origin of this structure's genetic information is named Eve because its genes are only inherited maternally. For 10 points, what non-nuclear genetic material is found in the organelle where cellular respiration takes place?", "answer": "mitochondrial DNA [or mtDNA; or M chromosome; or mitochondrial chromosome; accept answers mentioning both DNA and mitochondria or word forms or variants of either; prompt on answers mentioning \"mitochondria\" and \"genes\" or equivalents; do not accept or prompt on \"DNA\" alone]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This activity is the subject of an award-winning documentary directed by Jimmy Chin that shows Chin, Renan Ozturk, and another man's attempts to accomplish a notable \u28b8rst; in that \u28b8lm, one of this activity's leading practitioners, Conrad Anker, leads a group that does this activity at the \"Shark's Fin\" to honor Anker's mentor, Mugs Stump. The documentary Meru centers on this activity, which is central to a 2015 \u28b8lm in which Jason Clarke and Jake Gyllenhaal played Rob Hall and Scott Fischer, two real-life practitioners of it. In this activity, the danger of pulmonary edema can be mitigated by a drug called \"dex,\" and people doing it o0en use bottled oxygen. Jon Krakauer's book Into Thin Air discusses, for 10 points, what pastime that is central to the \u28b8lm Everest?", "answer": "mountain climbing [or mountaineering; accept rock climbing; prompt on \"hiking\"]", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "This character takes refuge in a chocolate factory and proclaims himself to be Jesus when he is assaulted by a gang whose members refer to themselves by code names such as \"Firestealer\" and \"Chicken Soup\"; shortly thereafter, this character joins that group, called \"The Dusters,\" and sets out to destroy government buildings. The two \"presumptive fathers\" of this character are a man who is executed for defending a post of\u28b8ce against an invasion force and a man who goes into seizures after swallowing a political party pin. This character uses his voice to shatter glass and, after reaching the age of three, refuses to grow. For 10 points, name this character who receives the title \"tin drum\" as a birthday gi0 in the \u28b8rst entry in Gu\u0308nter Grass's Danzig Trilogy.", "answer": "Oskar Matzerath [accept either underlined portion]", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A terrorist attack in this city was launched in response to Operation Agatha. Soldiers \u28b8ghting in this city's suburbs in an operation named after \"pitchforks\" set up forti\u28b8cations called \"Bevingrads.\" The al-Husayni family organized this city's guerilla \u28b8ghters into the \"Army of the Holy War.\" The Nebi Musa riots occurred in this city, which was led by mayor Teddy Kollek for most of the late 20th century. The United Nations dispatched Ralph Bunche (\"bunch\") to lead peace negotiations after his predecessor, Folke Bernadotte (\"FOAL\"-keh ber-nah-DOHT), was assassinated in this city by the Stern Gang. The British diplomatic presence in this city was wiped out when the Irgun bombed its King David Hotel. For 10 points, name this city where Muslim and Jewish residents fought over access to the Western Wall.", "answer": "Jerusalem [or Yerushalayim; or al-Quds]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One economist disputed traditional approaches to this situation by formulating eight design principles, including the use of \"graduated sanctions\"; that economist, Elinor Ostrom, wrote a book that offered governing methods in response to this situation. An essay about this situation begins by using the example of the nuclear arms race to illustrate a \"dilemma that has no technical solution\"; that 1968 essay, published in Science, references Thomas Malthus's writings on population to pose concerns about overpopulation and environmental sustainability in light of this situation, which is typically illustrated with the example of cattle grazing. Garrett Hardin titled an essay after, for 10 points, what situation in which self-interested individuals exploit a publicly available resource?", "answer": "tragedy of the commons [accept commons before \"arms race\"; prompt on \"commons\" a0er \"arms race\"]", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "The fact that twice applying a type of this operation always yields zero can be intuitively understood as \"the boundary of a boundary is nothing\"; that type of this operation gives an \"n plus one\" form for an n-form and is the exterior type. A matrix containing values to which this operation is applied is used for a change of variables via the substitution rule and is the Jacobian. The dot product of the gradient with a unit vector de\u28b8nes the directional type of this operation. A composition of functions requires the chain rule in order to perform this operation, which is de\u28b8ned as the limit as h goes to zero of the difference quotient \"f of x plus h\" minus \"f of x\" all over h. For 10 points, what calculus operation gives the rate of change of a variable?", "answer": "derivative [or obvious equivalents such as differentiation; or exterior derivative until \"change of variables\" is read]", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This artist designed and created a large \"picturesque\" landscape that was best observed from the \"Viewshed\" near the Calvert Vaux (VAWKS)\u00c2\u2013designed \"Cosy Cottage,\" where this man painted many of his works. This artist's travels in Persia inspired both a painting that looks through an opening in a rock onto the facade of a building known as \"the treasury\" and the name of his family home, Olana. This artist of El Khasne Petra was inspired by Alexander von Humboldt's book Cosmos to take a trip that inspired a massive landscape depicting two people in front of a rustic cross to the le0 of a large tropical waterfall. For 10 points, name this member of the Hudson River School whose trip to Ecuador led him to paint Cotopaxi and Heart of the Andes.", "answer": "Frederic Edwin Church", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "An essay by this author recalls a woman wearing a \"dirty crepe-de-Chine (crep-duh-sheen) wrapper\" who tells a bartender that Estelle is the reason she and George Sharp separated. This author explained that writing down anecdotes about others helps her to reconnect with her past selves in the essay \"On Keeping a Notebook.\" In another essay, this author wrote that for people who grew up out west, New York City is an \"in\u28b8nitely romantic notion\" rather than a \"plausible place\" to live, which is why she moved away. This author of \"Goodbye to All That\" described a Word document with the words \"life changes fast\" in a book about the death of her husband and the hospitalization of her daughter Quintana Roo (kwin-TAH-nuh ROO). For 10 points, name this Californian essayist who wrote The Year of Magical Thinking and Slouching Towards Bethlehem.", "answer": "Joan Didion", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}], "bonuses": []}